Guide to the Roberta Florence Brinkley papers, 1933-1962
Duke University. University Archives
Roberta Florence Brinkley papers 1933-1962
Duke University. University Archives
Brinkley, Roberta Florence, 1893-1967.
1.7 linear feet Extent: 1,750 Items
Educator and administrator Roberta Florence Brinkley was professor of English and Dean of the Woman's College at Duke University from 1947 until 1962. Collection contains manuscript materials, correspondence, class notes, memoranda, and other papers. The bulk consists of notes, drafts and a typescript of the unpublished Milton's Poems Adapted for Music, and related materials on the relationship of music and other arts, including the various versions and adaptations of Paradise Lost.
UA.29.02.0108
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Roberta Florence Brinkley papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1962, 1967, 1983.
Biographical Note
Educator and administrator Roberta Florence Brinkley was professor of English and Dean of the Woman's College at Duke University from 1947 until 1962. She was born in Augusta, Georgia, educated at Agnes Scott College (A.B., 1914), Peabody College for Teachers (M.A., 1919), and received her Ph.D. from Yale in 1924. Her area of study was English literature of the 17th century. She taught at Goucher College from 1924 to 1947, serving as chair of the English Department from 1945-1947. In 1947, she came to Duke to succeed Alice Mary Baldwin as Dean of the Woman's College and served in that capacity until her retirement in 1962. She wrote or edited five books and was active in a number of scholarly societies.
Collection Overview
Collection contains manuscript materials, correspondence, class notes, memoranda, and other papers. The bulk consists of notes, drafts and a typescript of the unpublished Milton's Poems Adapted for Music, and related materials on the relationship of music and other arts, including the various versions and adaptations of Paradise Lost. The remaining papers consist of notes for Dr. Brinkley's classes on English poetry, a typescript, memos, and correspondence concerning her activities with Duke University Church, and materials concerning art development at Duke. A copy of her eulogy, written by Dean Ellen Gobbel and Miriam Warren was added to the collection.
The manuscript of Milton's Poems Adapted for Music is on loan and is available for consultation but cannot be released without the permission of S.G. Brinkley.
Subject Headings
Art Education in the South Atlantic Area: The Place of Duke University; Art -- North Carolina -- Study and teaching -- Reports -- 1937; Brinkley, Roberta Florence, 1893-1967. Memorials; Duke University. Dept. of Fine Arts -- Planning -- 1937; Duke University Church; English literature -- 17th Century -- Study and teaching; Huckabee, Ellen Harris, 1907-1995 -- Writings; Milton, John; Duke University. Woman’s College -- Description
Related Material
Biographical Reference Collection, 1972-2004.
University Archives. Duke University.
Ellen Huckabee Gobbel Papers, 1924-1979.
University Archives. Duke University.
News Service Biographical Files, 1960-2004.
University Archives. Duke University.
Photograph Collection, 1861-2006.
University Archives. Duke University.
Woman's College records, 1928-1974.
University Archives. Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- Container List, 3 Boxes
  - Cards for Class Lectures (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1962 (Box 1)
  - Research notes: Norton Anthology, 2nd edition
    - Bibliography (Box 1)
    - Cantatas (Box 1)
    - Comus Adaptations (Box 1)
    - Comus and Arcades: Bibliography and comments (Box 1)
    - Conclusion (revised) (Box 1)
    - Copies of May Morning (Box 1)
    - Creation (Box 1)
    - Dryden, Stillingfleet, Arnold, and Jago (Box 1)
    - Introduction (revised) (Box 1)
    - L'Allegro and Il Penseroso: Miscellaneous material (Box 1)
    - L'Allegro and Il Penseroso: Reviews and criticism (Box 1)
    - Lycidas (Box 1)
    - Musical Times (Box 1)
    - Nativity Ode (Box 1)
    - Introduction and Conclusion (old and new versions) (Box 1)
    - Originals for Psalms (Box 1)
    - Originals: L'Allegro and Il Penseroso (Box 1)
    - Original: Handel's The Occasional Oratorio (Box 1)
    - Other Early Poems (Box 1)
    - Paradise Lost: 19th and 20th Centuries (Box 2)
    - [Untitled folder] (Box 2)
    - Prose (Box 2)
    - References for Psalms: Wesley (Box 2)
    - Samson - Handel (Box 2)
    - Samson write-ups (Box 2)
    - Short Units of Paradise Lost (Box 2)
    - Sixth Nightingale (Box 2)
    - Songs - Arcades and Comus (Box 2)
    - Sweet is the Breath and other shorter selections (Box 2)
    - Spicers - The Student's Manuscript Music Book (Box 2)
  - Art Development at Duke, 1936-1959 (Box 3)
  - Duke University Church, 1947-1953 (Box 3)
  - Brinkley, R. Florence, Papers AAUW, Eulogy, Oct. 9, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Brinkley, R. Florence, The Woman's College typescript, 1957 (Box 3)
  - Brinkley, R. Florence, Milton's Poem Adapted for Music, manuscript, (2 folders) [RESTRICTED] (Box 3)